RG 003, New London County, County Court Papers By Subject
Connecticut State Library
New London County, County Court papers by subject
1685-1856
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. County Court (New London County)
52 cubic feet
Papers by Subject is an artificial collection consisting of materials removed from New London County Court Files series by State Library staff after the records were received from the New London court. Subjects include: Admissions to the Bar; Appointment of Officers; Confiscated Estates and Loyalists; Conservators and Guardians; Costs; Court Expenses; Executions; Inquests; Insolvents; Jurors; Licenses; Meeting House; Militia; Miscellaneous; Partition of Lands; Pensions, Revolutionary War; Summons for Evidence; Travel.
RG003_NLCC_PBS
1921-029
Historical Note
The New London County. County Court. Papers by Subject Collection consists of materials that were removed from the original papers of the Court after the records were acquired by the Connecticut State Library in 1921, a procedure that is not consistent with modern archival principles.1
Materials moved from Files to Papers by Subject are often identified by cross-reference (x-refs) cards with the original Files, but not every subseries is identified by x-refs.2 Each x-ref includes the case name, court term at which the case was heard, the place to which the papers are removed, the original docket number, and a second number written in pencil to provide more precise identification of the item removed. The first pencil document number (1) appears on a June 1855 x-ref and the numbers increase as one goes back in time.3
Endnotes
1Records of the New London County Court are divided into four major series - Dockets, Trials, Files, and Papers by Subject. For more information on the history of county courts and these records, please see the finding aid for New London County. County Court. Files, 1691-1855.
2The major subseries identified by x-refs include, Admissions to the Bar, Appointment of Officers, Costs, Court Expenses, Indians, Licenses, Miscellaneous, Partition Lands, and Travel.
3The following numbers are used in June 1855: No. 1 - Indians; No. 2 - Travel; No. 3 - Admissions to the Bar; and No. 4 - Costs.
Scope and Content
The records are arranged under eighteen headings or series, from Admissions to the Bar to Travel. The papers in most series are arranged in chronological order. Only a handful of documents exist for the period before 1700. Well over 99% of the papers date from the years between 1700 and 1855.
The first series is Admissions to the Bar (Box 1, folders 1-10). The applications stated that the person had received legal training and some were endorsed by lawyers who were already practicing before the New London County Court. The first such petition, dated June 23, 1768, urged the admission of Solomon Kellog and was signed by fifteen practicing attorneys, virtually the entire complement of regulars.4 The 1788 application of Roger Eells of Norwich included a letter of recommendation from Governor Samuel Huntington.5 The records contain a handful of admissions from prominent Connecticut political figures, like Roger Griswold, Henry M. Wait, Lafayette Foster, and John T. Wait. Admissions were also sometimes recorded in Trials, usually at the beginning of the records for court sessions.6
Series two consists of records of Appointment of Officers (Box 1, folders 11-20, Box 2, folders 1-9). An early document records a decision of the county court in November 1781 to separate the offices of clerk and treasurer, a consequence of an event "on the Sixth of Sep[tembe]r Last," whereby the "records, Files, Securities, and all Entries pertaining to the County Treasurer & Clerks Offices were Burnt & Consumed by Fire when the Enemy Burnt New London."7 The appointments and resignations cover such offices as county clerk, county treasurer, collectors of duties on imports, collectors of excise, jailer, inspector of fish, packer of beef and pork, sheriff and sheriff's deputy, state's attorney, and town surveyor.
The small one-folder Confiscated Estates and Loyalists series contains a small group of documents pertaining to James Rogers (New London) and Elisha Beckwith (Lyme).
Conservators and Guardians represent one of the more significant groupings of records in Papers by Subject. Filling around five boxes, these records are arranged alphabetically by surname of person who needed a conservator or guardian. Conservators or overseers were chosen to take care of mentally incompetent adults, while guardians were appointed over orphan children. Petitioners used several phrases to describe the condition of people requiring a conservator. The expressions included, "labouring under a state of mental derangement," "by age, sickness & bodily infirmity... now is impotent & unable to provide for himself," "impotent & insane," "Lunatic," "impotent and non compos mentis," "a State of Distraction," "naturally wanting in understanding," and other similar phrases.8 These memorials provide a good overview of the condition of those with mental impairments and how society dealt with them.
Selectmen or relatives submitted memorials to have guardians or overseers appointed over the mentally ill and distracted. Eight relatives of Mrs. Anne Johnson of Lyme submitted a memorial to the County Court on March 13, 1805. They stated that their father John Johnson died intestate leaving an estate worth £1,400, that the "widow Mrs. Anne Johnson hath by age & bodily infirmity become impotent in mind & understanding," and that her son John Johnson, heir to one-seventh of the estate, "from birth hath been a cripple & who hath always been naturally wanting in understanding & wholly incapable of providing for himself." They requested that conservators be appointed for Anne and John. The court appointed a conservator for son John but not for widow Anne.9 In two instances, the court appointed conservators over men who had been injured in the Revolutionary War. In the first case, John Perkins of Norwich asked the court to appoint a conservator over his son Dr. Abisha who had been captured by the British while on a privateering cruise and confined to jail for two years, "Dureing which time he was Exercised with a most Severe fit of Sickness and Indured almost Every other Hardship which the hand of Cruelty Could Inflict, by means whereof he was flung into the most Distressing Fitts" and had become "wholly unable to tak Care of him Self."10 In February 1785, Samuel Bishop of Norwich asked the county court to appoint an overseer for his son Nathaniel. An officer in the Army, Samuel due to "Hardship & misfortunes... his Debility is Such as Render him wholly uncapable of taking care of himself."11
Sometimes individuals petitioned to be released from the care of a conservator. Richard Atwell of New London unsuccessfully pleaded in 1782 to be released from the care of an overseer because "he is not reduced to want, nor likely to be reduced to want, by idleness, mismanagement or bad husbandry."12 In a second case, Thomas Halsey, a free Negro who had been manumitted in 1779 and possessed an estate worth $2,500, petitioned that "he hath always enjoyed the privileges of a Citizen in all Respects except the Right of Suffrage in the Town of Groton," but that in 1808 the selectmen "maliciously appointed" Philip Gray as his overseer and Gray was determined to take over control of the petitioner's property. The court granted his memorial.13
Only a small minority of the files consists of memorials for guardians of minor children. The 1709 case of Richard Ely, son of Richard Ely deceased, represents one of the more interesting. His widow Mary Starling petitioned to become guardian of her son in place of the youth's uncle Capt. William Ely. The widow claimed that William Ely was "unjustly indeavering to tacke away my Sone Richard Ely from me" and wanted to make certain that the boy's inheritance was preserved.15
Next comes around nineteen boxes of Costs. They lack the interest of several other subseries in Papers by Subject, but do provide some supplementary information to that found in Trials and Files. For example, in June 1705, John Arnold presented his bill for serving as attorney for defendant George Walker. The itemized bill asked for payment of £0-1-0 for bail bond, £0-1-0 for copying a writ, and £0-3-0 for three days' attendance at court.16 In 1719, Costs contain a list of fines and forfeitures due County Treasurer George Denison at the time of his death.16 The bill of Samuel Peck of Lyme against William Waller came a few years later and it included charges for making copies from Lyme town records, from proprietors' records, two deeds, and a survey.17 Costs for June 1742 include a sheriff's bill for £16 and king's attorney bill of £2.18
Although the overwhelming majority of costs included are those from individual lawsuits, other expenses are also found. They include bills of costs for laying out highways, for repair and upkeep on the Norwich and New London jails, for repair work on the courthouse, for cleaning, ringing bell, and starting fires at the courthouse, and for punch, flip, wine, and dinners for court officers. In addition, they hold jailer bills, fees for whipping delinquents, and beginning in 1839 a whole series of bills jailers submitted for the care of prisoners.19 Moreover, Costs also include a small scattering of other records, among them petitions, pleadings, presentments, and testimonies.
Court Expenses, encompassing a half box, are similar in character to Costs. They contain expenses of town constables, county officers, printing, court meals, and for transporting prisoners.
Executions comprise the largest and in some ways the most valuable series in Papers by Subject.20 Executions fill almost forty-six boxes of records from 1700 to 1855. The records are alphabetically arranged by groups of years, e.g. 1700-1720, 1721-1725, and 1750-1759 and arranged alphabetically by name of the winning party except in instances in which the colony or state successfully prosecutes in a criminal action. In such cases, the convicted party is interfiled with the names of winning parties. The county court issued writs of execution to the losing party in a court case to recover the debt, costs of suit, or fine levied. Sometimes the person upon whom the execution was served paid the money due, but often real property and/or personal property was seized and sold at auction to recover the debt. If the losing party lacked the means to pay the debt, he was generally jailed. In other instances, the debtor absconded and the plaintiff never recovered the amount that was owed. Although the series contains valuable documentation to supplement that found in Files, many court cases found in the former do not find any representation in Papers by Subject. They include lawsuits that were withdrawn, no appearance cases, and those in which fines were paid immediately upon conviction.
Land, livestock, household goods, and occasionally parts of dwellings were auctioned off to pay debts. To cite one example, when John Waterman, Jr. recovered judgment against Joseph Tracy in 1726 for £117-17-2 debt and costs of suit, the deputy sheriff, "By Vertue of this Execution" seized "one hundred and fourty Goats and fourteen Mares and yearlin Coults" and advertised for their sale.21 Nathaniel Beckwith of Lyme owed Samuel Bishop of New London £10-15. He refused to pay, offer any estate upon which to levy the execution, or to choose anyone to assist in appraising his estate, thus the creditor "Tenderd... a Certain Dwelling House... Being the Estate of the Said Debtor. The deputy sheriff chose two appraisers and they appraised "the West Room from Group Upwards with the Land it Stands on and the Privilege of ye Door yard and the One Half of the Chimney and the Entry Way" worth £11-13-8."22 On occasion, an extensive list of household goods was sold as in the case of David Lothrop and Joshua Lothrop v. Park Woodward. The creditors, Norwich merchants, recovered judgment against the Groton defendant for £24-12-6. The execution includes a three-page list of household goods sold, the price of each, and the party to whom each item was sold.23
The case of Christopher Denison v. Cyprian Sterry, both of Preston, provide a good example of the process of seizure of property by writ of execution and its disposition. In February 1754, constable Silas Park delivered an execution to Sterry.
"Then by Virtue of this Execution I Leveyed the Same on two Indian Boys tendered to me by the Within Christopher Denison as the Estate of ye within Named Cyprean Stery and Posted them to be Sold at the Sign Post in sd. Preston on the 27th Instant at the Beat of the Drum to the highest Bidder and on the 27th of February I Caused the Drum to Beat at the sd. Post and then Sold the Sd. Boys to the heist Bidder viz one to Ephraim Smith for £116-17-0 and the other to Christopher Tracey for £110-0-0."24
By the third decade of the nineteenth century, the nature of executions began to change, as they recorded criminal offenses and fines, jail time, and occasional whippings. In one such case, "Diana, alias Dinah, a woman of Colour" was convicted of theft, sent to the county jail, and whipped five stripes on the naked back.27 Crimes meriting jail time, either in the county facility or the state prisons at Newgate and Wethersfield, included arson, adultery, assault, attempted murder, attempted rape, bigamy, breaking and entering, burglary, fathering a bastard child, horse stealing, passing counterfeit money, and theft.
After imprisonment for debt was abolished for women in 1826 and for men under most circumstances in 1837, officers of the court sometimes were unsuccessful in levying writs of execution.26 In one case in 1846, constable Henry F. Bentley of North Stonington had to report his failure to serve the writ of execution for $5.36 on Spooner Crapo. "Then I received this Execution & Repaired to the Debtors place of abode & demand[ed] of him the amount of this Execution which he neglected and refused, whereupon I continued to search for goods & estate to satisfy the same until Jan. 9th 1847 when I return this Execution unto court wholly unsatisfied."27
Someone interested in studying debt in southeastern Connecticut in detail will find Executions extremely useful. One can track writs of execution by several categories - paid in cash, real property seized, personal property seized, defendant jailed, and defendant absconded - and changes over time. Impressionistic evidence indicates that the percentage of losing parties unable to pay their debts and either sent to jail or leaving for parts unknown increased immediately after the American Revolution.
The series for Indians has been separated from the rest of Papers by Subject. Demand for these records by parties of opposing sides in tribal recognition controversies and by those seeking to find their Native American roots has been so great that the originals have been restricted and, photocopies made available to researchers. These records are now treated as a distinct collection.
One folder of Inquests follows, as most inquests are located in Papers by Subject for the Superior Court, and then one folder of Insolvents.
Jurors, fills just over eight boxes, all of Boxes 73-80 and four folders of Box 81. The records are arranged alphabetically by town in two chronological sequences - 1700-1844 and 1845-1855. The records consist of summons for a specific number of jurors from each town to appear at the forthcoming session of the county court, together with a listing of the persons so designated.28 The first item in the subseries comes from the town of Bozrah, incorporated in May 1786 and hived off from Norwich. County Clerk Winthrop Saltonstall on November 3, 1787 summoned "One able and judicious Juryman a lawful Freeholder of said Town of Bozra[h] to attend the County Court to be holden at Norwich... Fourth Tuesday of November Instant."29 Each town kept a box containing the names of potential jurors and names were drawn out to fill the quota. The Bozrah constable noted that "This day I read the within writ in the hearing of Jesse Abel who was drawn out of the Box of Jurors." After the American Revolution, documentation also included mileage and payments for mileage for those selected.
The eleventh series in Papers by Subjects consists of Licenses, filling a little more than one box. Arranged alphabetically by surname and covering the period from 1702 to 1855, they consist of applications to the court for licenses in the "art & mistery of Tanning" leather. The applications were endorsed by selectmen, licensed tanners, or by a certification that the applicant had served an apprenticeship. These license applications provide useful data on relationships among tanners in New London County towns. To cite just one example, Daniel Miner of Lyme, the Separatist minister, applied for a tanning license in June 1759. Licensed tanners Abraham Perkins and Elijah Peck certified his application. Miner in turn subsequently endorsed the petitions of Lyme candidates George Lewis, Frederick Mather, George Read, and Elijah Peck, Jr. Tanning had the tendency to run in families. Over the course of some sixty years in the eighteenth century, six Gallups from Groton following the tanning trade - Ben Adam Gallup, Jr. (1737), Nathaniel Gallup (1741), Elisha Gallup (1750), Capt. Joseph Gallup (1750), Prentis Gallup (1768), and Lodowick Gallup (1796).
The Meeting House series (parts of Boxes 81-82) is small but contains much interesting material. The bulk of the records consist of papers concerning the building of meetinghouses by established Congregational churches. The documents include materials on New Chelsea, New Concord, and Newent societies in Norwich, together with a small group of papers on Chesterfield, a parish located in Colchester, Lyme, and New London that never had the resources to properly organize. One folder (Box 82, folder 2) consists of scattered materials on New London County Baptists, Rogerenes, and Separatists from 1730 to 1765.
The records contain one folder of Militia and the bulk of the papers concerns 1747 lawsuits instituted by King's Attorney Matthew Griswold against several men for failure to serve on the colony sloop Defence.
Almost two boxes of Miscellaneous follow. Subjects found in Miscellaneous include Common Fields, Court House, Fishing, Gaol/Jail, James Rogers and Samuel Beebe, Joan (a slave), Lottery, and Miscellaneous. Common Fields contains a 1749 petition of the proprietors of "Ely's Meadow or Six mile Island farm" in Lyme, Court House documents include materials on the building of a new court house in New London in 1784, while Gaol materials include a number of late 18th and 19th century petitions to extend prison bounds." One such 1807 document petitioned to extend the bounds of the Norwich prison "to include the Slaughter house & yard lately erected by Mr. Gardner Carpenter."30 Also included is material on an interesting 1715 case of horse theft, the complainant being Thomas Sanders of Poughkeepsie, New York and the defendants John Chadwick, John Tillitson, and David Tillitson of Lyme.31
Perhaps the most significant files in Miscellaneous are those of James Rogers and Samuel Beebe (Box 83, folders 1-2) and Joan (slave) (Box 83, folder 4). The papers in these three folders cover the period 1688-1718 and contain information on the ownership of Joan based upon the will of James Rogers and documentation on various lawsuits over her ownership. Additional material on Joan, wife of John Jackson, and their family is found in the finding aid to New London County African Americans Collection.
Miscellaneous also contains twelve folders of papers called Miscellaneous. They hold a variety of unrelated documents, among them a copy of 1685-86 New London town records regarding the hiring of a new minister, a 1725 letter of James Sterling complaining that shipwright John Jeffrey of Groton had not built his ship according to specifications, a 1764 Rogerene document giving the marriage oath used by the tiny sect, and an 1815 memorial from the selectmen of Norwich concerning the morals of children working in a cotton factory.32
The next series, Partition of Lands, fills four folders, and covers the period 1745-1832. Caused by disputes among estate heirs, they provide excellent genealogical data on the parties concerned. One such case is Jacob Sollard and his wife Sarah v. Joseph Rogers, Sarah Rogers single woman, Joshua Champion, Jr. as guardian to Jonathan Rogers and Ezekiel Rogers, Alice Rogers as guardian to Stephen Rogers, and Lucretia Rogers for the partition of land in Lyme.33 Partitions for the period up to 1745 are found in Files.
Pensions, Revolution War comprise series 16. In 1818, the Congress of the United States passed legislation to grant pensions to non-disabled veterans of the War of Independence. Subsequent 1820 legislation limited pension rights only to those living in poverty.34 This series contains 154 alphabetically arranged pension documents, about two dozen from minorities.35 Each pensioner had to submit a form describing his military service together with a report on his limited economic means. The form also included the pensioner's age, place of residence, and names of family members.
The documents do not contain much detail about military service, but some interesting pieces of information appear. Joseph Church served in 1776 under Capt. Nathan Hale, Phineas Hyde served on the Continental ship Confederacy under Capt. Seth Harding, Ezra Lee piloted Bushnell's submarine Turtle, and Thomas Pool was an officer in the regiment of light dragoons commanded by Col. Elisha Sheldon. The statement of Elijah Taylor of Colchester is typical. Taylor wrote that he was a laborer with a lame hand caused by the loss of two fingers and, "therefore cant obtain but small Wages." His wife Abigail was in poor health and daughter Sophia "wholly incapable of supporting herself. He owned no property except a "Small shell of a house built by the charity of my Neighbours." This entire estate was worth $16.25.36
Series 17, Summons for Evidence, fills the next six boxes.37 It covers the years between 1700 and 1768. Thereafter, Summons for Evidence materials are located in the records for Files. The information contained in Summons for Evidence supplements that found in Files, but only includes materials from adjudicated cases, not from defaults and those withdrawn. The first document summons James Springer and David Cullver to appear in June 1700 in Joseph Wells v. Theophilus Stanton, a dispute over the ownership of a colt.38 Another early summons is for William Stark and his son William in a case concerning breach of the Sabbath for fishing on Sunday.39 Although most summonses are routine, they sometimes provide useful tidbits of information. For example, the court summoned Thomas Jones of Colchester in February 1725 "to defend the Title to One hundred and twenty Acres of Land, which he sold to Robert Denison Junr.. March 6th 1721/2 which Land lyeth in New London North Parish and ye Title thereof will come in dispute between John Rowland and Jonathan Rogers, Plt., and Robert Denison, Defendt."40 In another instance, Samuel Fox of New London was summoned to provide a bill of sale for "A Negro woman... Named Marrian" and sold to Nathaniel Lothrop.41 Most summonses, however, merely required those named to appear and give evidence in a particular case. Other materials include bonds, depositions and court testimonies, jury verdicts, petitions, pleadings, and presentments, as Summons for Evidence served as a catchall for a variety of miscellaneous documents on court cases and researchers may well find information of interest.